Today's דף daf *daf* is דף daf יוד גימל *daf Yud Gimmel*.
We pick up at the bottom of... יוד דלת *Yud Daled*? No,
יוד גימל *Yud Gimmel*, but we pick up at the bottom of
יוד בית bayit עמוד בית *Yud Bais Amud Bais*. Today is יוד
גימל *Yud Gimmel*?
No, we're at יוד אלף *Yud Aleph* halfway down on עמוד בית
*Amud Bais*.
Oh, my דף daf *daf* is folded over! I was looking at
it, I'm sorry. Okay. Today's דף *daf*, today's דף *daf*, sorry, thank
you.
And that's been recorded.
Today's דף *daf* is יוד בית *Yud Bais*, we start at the
bottom halfway at the bottom of יוד אלף עמוד בית *Yud Aleph
Amud Bais*. Thank you. Okay, so the discussion is what they would
do with the קטורת Ktores *Ketoret*, how they would desanctify and resanctify
the קטורת Ktores. *Ketoret* for use in the coming year. And we
had the whole thing about transferring the value and paying them and
buying it back and so on. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
has a debate
whether when you make the קטורת Ktores *Ketoret*, you have to make
it in a כלי שרת keli shares. *Kli Shares* or not. Okay,
and this is two opinions. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei בר רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina's *Rabbi Yossi bar Rabbi Chanina* says you have to make
it in a כלי שרת keli shares. *Kli Shares*, and רבי יהושע
Reb Yehoshua בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* says you do not.
And now we pick up with the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that says
the following.
The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says... one minute... okay, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אמר רבי יוסי amar Rabbi Yossi, בר רבי Rebbi בון *Amar
Rabbi Yossi bar Rabbi Bun* right where there's like a little בית
*beis* in parentheses, is that a בית *beis*? No, a little גימל
*gimmel* in parentheses about halfway down. אמר רבי יוסי בר רבי בון
אתיא דרבי יוסי בן חנניה כשמואל *Amar Rabbi Yossi bar Rabbi Bun
Atia d'Rabbi Yossi ben Chananya k'Shmuel*. רבי יוסי בן חנניה
*Rabbi Yossi ben Chananya* that says that it is invalid goes like
שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel*, ורבי יהושע בן לוי *v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* who
says it's valid in a non כלי שרת keli shares *Kli Shares*
goes כרבי יוחנן *k'Rabbi Yochanan*. דתנינן *Detaninan*, now let's show how this
lines up.
We teach in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, it's actually the next משנה
Mishna *Mishnah* coming up: המקדיש נכסיו והיו בהן דברים ראויים לקרבנות ציבור
Haktish nechasav vehayu bahen devarim reuyim lekorbanot tzibur, *Hamakdish nechasav v'hayu bahen
devarim reuyim lekorbanot tzibur*. Somebody basically says, I sanctify all my property
to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*. Now סתם stam. *stam*,
when somebody says that to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*,
it means to the בדק הבית Bedek Habayis, *Bedek Habayit*, okay, to
the funds for repairing the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit Hamikdash*. But
let's say amongst his property are some animals. So we're going to
see in the upcoming משנה mishna, *Mishnah* whether the fact that those
are fit for קרבנות korbanos *korbanot*, does it automatically mean that the
generic הקדש hekdesh. *hektesh* for them becomes for קרבנות korbanos, *korbanot* or
not? There's another position which basically says, well, the הקדש hekdesh, *hektesh*
doesn't become for קרבנות korbanos, *korbanot*, it is for בדק הבית bedek
habayit, *Bedek Habayit*, but you have to make sure you use the
animals for קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* because they're in the פרשה parsha, *parsha*.
So we'll see how that all plays out in the next משנה
mishna *Mishnah*. But here's the line that we're going to focus on.
It says... let now normally if the discussion is if there are
animals do they be brought as קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*, that's when they
could be brought as my private קרבן korban *korban*, I'm the one
sanctifying it. But let's say there's something in my property that could
only be used for a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur, *korban tzibur*. Okay,
now what's the only thing that can only be used for a
קרבן ציבור korban tzibur, *korban tzibur*? Any animal, any flower, anything like
that can always be used for a קרבן יחיד korban yachid, *korban
yachid*. So what is the thing that's ראוי roy לקרבן ציבור tzibur.
*raui lekurban tzibur*? So רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar קטורת Ktores
*Rabbi Yochanan amar ketoret*. The only thing I could be having in
my property that's fit for a קרבן ציבור Korban tzibur, *korban tzibur*
and not for a קרבן יחיד korban yachid, *korban yachid* is the
קטורת Ktores *ketoret*. And now the question is, okay,
what do you do with this קטורת Ktores *ketoret*, you know, how
do you redeem it, what do you use it for, and so
on. But there's one opinion there that you actually, you know, might
use it for the קטורת Ktores *ketoret* itself, or at least it's
considered to be fit for the קטורת Ktores *ketoret* itself. There's only
a little bit of a problem. If you need to make the
קטורת Ktores *ketoret* in a כלי שרת keli shares. *Kli Shares*, how
could the קטורת Ktores *ketoret* that happens to be lying around in
my house be
fit right for the קטורת Ktores *ketoret* for
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit Hamikdash*? Unless you're one of the
people who made it.
Ah, so it says אמר רבי הושעיה תיפתר *Amar Rabbi Hoshaia tipatrah*...
you can explain it... באומן משל בית אבטינס *b'uman mishel Beit Avtinas*...
so either you're one of the people that made it... שהיה נוטל
בשכרו קטורת Ktores *shehayah notel b'scharo ketoret*. So either you made it
in a כלי שרת keli shares, *Kli Shares* but then why would
it be yours to sanctify? So I can't give that answer. But
what it says is, you remember we talked before that they would
sometimes use the קטורת ketoret, *ketoret* to pay the workers. So basically,
you had קטורת ketoret *ketoret* that was made in the בית המקדש
beis hamikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*, it came to the end of the year,
we had some leftover, we desanctified it, we used it to pay
the workers. Now they have in their house קטורת ketoret, *ketoret* that
they own that was made in a כלי שרת keli shares, *Kli
Shares*. And then when they sanctify it, now in theory it could
be used for the קטורת ketoret. *ketoret* in the בית המקדש beis
hamikdash.
*Beit Hamikdash*. But the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* was made in a לשכה
lishka *lishkah* in the מקדש *Mikdash*, it wasn't some workshop in town.
Okay, so that's not clear either. In theory, you could talk about
it being made in a כלי שרת keli shares, *Kli Shares* outside
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit Hamikdash*. The general assumption would be
that anything in a כלי שרת keli shares, *Kli Shares* would be
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit Hamikdash*, okay,
but wherever it was, you know, how do you get that קטורת
ketoret *ketoret* that was made in a כלי שרת keli shares. *Kli
Shares*? And the answer is you got it because we paid you
with it. And it was initially sanctified, now we paid you with
it, now when you sanctify your property, it's fit for the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*.
There are other problems like having it lying around because I know
there's a very big taboo, if you make it in your own
house then you're liable by כרת *kares*.
So like, you know, it's a bit... No, and
now that it's been desanctified...
Okay, so I can smell it all I want and I could
use it for my...
Yeah, once it's been desanctified. Right. Now, point you should say is
that before we said you didn't actually pay them with the קטורת.
ketoret, You use the קטורת ketoret, in this whole exchange, but in
the end you paid them with money. But we'll look in the
see in the next משנה mishna, the possibility that you might have
actually paid them with the קטורת. ketoret Okay, so that deals with
that problem. Now we go on. דאמר רבי יוסי בי רבי חנינא
כשמואל, De'amar Rabbi Yosei BeRabbi Chanina keShmuel, רבי יוסי from רבי חנינא's
who says that it's פסול pasul to do outside, to do outside
of a כלי שרת. keli shares, That's consistent with שמואל. Shmuel How
do you know? דאמר רב הונא משמיה דשמואל, De'amar Rav Huna mishmei
deShmuel, מכתשת עשו אותה ככלי שרת לקדש, machteishet asu osah kekeli shares
lekadeish, that he says explicitly in the name of שמואל Shmuel's that
the grinder, the spice grinder, the קטורת ketoret grinder, they made into
a כלי שרת. keli shares He says ככלי שרת. kekeli shares. Doesn't
mean... Yeah, but the understanding is, they... I... it's true, but the
גמרא Gemara is not emphasizing the כ. chof. They made it into
a כלי שרת keli shares. in order that it would sanctify the
קטורת ketoret. that was put into it when it was made. So,
assuming that would be a necessary part of how the קטורת ketoret.
was made. Okay. אמר רבי יוסי בי רבי בון, Amar Rabbi Yosei
BeRabbi Bun, אמר רבי חוני קמי רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Chuni kamei
Rabbi Yosei, דבר שקידש ככלי שרת. davar shekideish kekeli shares. Now we're
going to have a question if you say that the קטורת ketoret
was made in a כלי שרת. kly sharet, Because we have a
principle. Something that was sanctified in a כלי שרת, klei sharet? he
says נפדה? nifdeh? Could it be redeemed? Meaning, I assume you know
that the הלכה halacha is you can't redeem a קרבן korban. unless
it has a מום. mum. Things that are sanctified for בדק הבית,
bedek habayit. however, for their value, not for their use, can be
redeemed. Other types of things, you know, let's say I sanctified this
stone and I want it to be put in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash So that's for its use, it's not for its value,
but still I can redeem it; it's not a קרבן. korban But
once something is sanctified in a כלי שרת, kli sharet? okay, then
it's going to be intrinsically used, the thing itself, it cannot be
redeemed. So how could you do this whole... this whole thing with
the קטורת ketoret and use it to redeem it and rebuy it
if you say that you need to make the קטורת ketoret in
a כלי שרת, kli sharet right? The הלכה halacha is it can't
be redeemed. So now we're going to get an answer to this
which basically also answers all the other exceptions we've had before about
how certain things, you know, how can you use the תרומת הלשכה
trumas halishka to pay for certain things which are not קרבנות korbanot
and so on. So let's take a look. Doesn't this violate the
rules? If it's sanctified in כלי שרת, how do you redeem it?
So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, ולא דשמואל
היא? velo deShmuel hi? One minute. We said that this is שמואל's
Shmuel position that says you use the כלי שרת. דשמואל אמר, DeShmuel
amar, and שמואל Shmuel says, קל הוא במותר. kal hu bemossar. It's
a leniency with leftover things. Basically, somehow בית דין Beis Din stipulate
that although we use the funds and whatever and we buy all
these קרבנות, korbanot, if they are going to wind up being leftover
for קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur not קרבן korban. יחיד, yachid all rules
will still apply for קרבן korban יחיד, yachid but for קרבן ציבור,
korban tzibbur if things are leftover, then we have more flexibility in
terms of how to deal with the הקדש. hekdesh, Sort of like
we said before, you know, תרומת הלשכה trumas halishka was supposed to
be for קרבנות, korbanot. but we also can use it for other
things, and then we'll say it won't have been sanctified. We'll have
that flexibility. How do you know that שמואל Shmuel says this? Something
like leftover now is not
really sanctified, something like that.
It never explains the mechanics. די פלג Di pelag because there was
a debate. הותירו תמימים, Hossiru temimim, let's say there were left over
unblemished קרבנות korbanot at the end of the year. You had some
sheep that you sanctified and now it's ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh
Nissan and you have to... can't use it because it's old year...
bought with old year funds? Right, exactly. So what do you do
with it? So שמואל אמר נפדין תמימין. Shmuel amar nifdin temimim. Yeah,
you redeem it even though it's unblemished, which completely violates the rules.
רבי יוחנן אמר לא נפדין כפסולי המוקדשין. Rabbi Yochanan amar lo nifdin
kefsulei hamukdashim. You wait until it gets a מום mum and you
redeem it and you follow the rules. So you see that the
same issue we said before, that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and שמואל
Shmuel disagreed whether the קטורת ketoret was made with a כלי שרת,
parallels this debate that שמואל Shmuel. says even things that normally you
wouldn't be able to redeem, we'll give you some latitude to redeem,
so he can have the קטורת ketoret. if they're ציבור. tzibur The
קטורת made with a כלי שרת and you redeem it. He can
have a קרבן korban? that's a ציבור tzibur. and you redeem it
at the end of the year. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
no, it has to follow the rules. So if that's true, if
the animal is left over, you have to wait for it to
get a מום, mum, and the קטורת wasn't made with a כלי
שרת. So this is the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
שמואל. Shmuel's But yes, as Michael asked, the גמרא Gemara does not
tell you the mechanics of שמואל's Shmuel? approach.
Let's keep on going. הותירו שעירים. Hossiru se'irim.
Let's say what's left over at the end of the year is
not animals you were going to be using for an עולה, ola,
but a goat, a male goat, which you would use for a
חטאת. chatas. What would be the story with that according to שמואל?
Shmuel, על דעתיה דשמואל. Al da'ateih deShmuel. So would you be able
to redeem something that would have been set aside for a חטאת?
chatas?
קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur right?
He's saying ציבור. tzibbur, It was going to be used for a
מוסף, mussaf, okay, for the חטאת chatas for a מוסף. mussaf. אם
עולה נפדית לא כל שכן חטאת? Im ola nifdeis lo kol sheken
chatas?
So if an עולה ola can be redeemed, how much more so
a חטאת? chatas? Now why is it a קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
Is not so clear.
קרבן עדה Korban Edah says the קל וחומר kal vachomer is because
even after you redeem it... let's say I redeem this sheep that's
an עולה ola and then I redeem it because I have to
use... now I need to use new funds... to buy it. What
am I going to do with the sheep? So we're going to
see as I already indicated to you in the next משנה mishna,
that basically once something was in the פרשה, parsha you know, we
don't want it to not be used for a קרבן. korban. So
even though now it's desanctified, you want to—to buy it and resanctify
it. Okay? And that's what you're going to want to do. So
what? לכתחילה? lechatchila? Yeah, לכתחילה lechatchila you would דווקא davka want to
do that. Okay? So that's what you would do with an עולה.
olah. Now what would you do with a חטאת? chatas? You would
transfer the sanctity and then you would want to repurchase it as
a חטאת. chatas. Now why is that a קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
Hold on, let me remind myself why he says it's a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. One second.
חטאות chatasos that could be...
זכרון חנוך, Zichron Chanoch, right?
חטאת הציבור. chatas hatzibbur.
Oh,
so he says here's the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. The קל וחומר
kal vachomer is the following: if we didn't redeem it, if we
didn't do this trick and allowed ourselves to do it when it
was תמים, tamim, what would we normally have done? So by the
case of the עולה, olah, we would have waited for it to
get a מום mum and then we would have used the money
to go for an עולה, olah, and obviously you can't use the
original animal now it has a מום. mum. In the case of
the חטאת, chatas, we would have waited for it to get a
מום, mum, and the הלכה halacha is a חטאת chatas of a
יחיד yachid you can't redeem. But a חטאת chatas of a ציבור,
tzibbur if it has a מום, mum, everybody agrees you can redeem,
and the money would have gone for קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbeach for
an עולה. olah. So he says like this: Look, in the עולה
olah case, we redeem it and you know, even if we haven't
redeemed it, it would have stayed in the פרשה parsha. of an
עולה. olah. But in the חטאת chatas case, if we hadn't redeemed
it and we waited for it to get a מום, mum, it
never would have been used as a חטאת. chatas. The money only
would have gone as an עולה. olah. By allowing us to redeem
it when it's a תמים, tamim, this is the way the קרבן
העדה Korban HaEda explains it, we allow the original animal to be
reused as a חטאת chatas and still keep it in the פרשה.
parsha. So that's how he explains the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So
the basic answer so is, שמואל, Shmuel same way he allows you
to do it by an עולה olah of a ציבור tzibur to
redeem it on blemish, he would allow it as a חטאת. chatas.
על דעתיה דרבי יוחנן, al daateih d'Rabbi Yochanan, אמר
רב זירא, amar Rav Zeira, ירעו. yireu. But according to רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, we go by the rule. So rather than redeeming it
on blemish, we wait for it to get a blemish. Okay. So
that's the debate about what latitude we have with things at the
end of the שנה. shana. אמר רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק, amar
Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak, מקייצין בהן את המזבח. m'kayitzin bahen es
hamizbeach. And what would you do after it got a blemish? You
would go ahead and use it for קיץ המזבח, kayitz hamizbeach, the
funds towards that.
Or it could be something even more radical, he could be saying
even without it getting a blemish, you automatically
re—I'm sorry, he's saying not could be, he is, because we'll see
in the next piece of the גמרא. Gemara So one opinion is
you wait for it to get a blemish, you redeem it, you
use the money for עולה olah for קיץ המזבח, kayitz hamizbeach, that's
the normal thing. Now רב שמואל בר רב יצחק Rav Shmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak says a more radical thing. He says you actually take
this חטאת, chatas, right, that was—that at the end of the year
and what do you do? You repurpose it as an עולה. olah.
מקייצין בהן את המזבח. m'kayitzin bahen es hamizbeach. You repurpose it as
an עולה. olah. This is a שעיר seir for חטאת chatas and
you repurpose it as an עולה. olah. So the גמרא Gemara asks
because an עולה olah is male and the שעיר seir of חטאת—a
chatas חטאת ציבור chatas tzibbur is male, right? It's a שעיר לחטאת.
seir l'chatas. So this is like wild. So the גמרא gemara, says
וקשיא יש חטאת שקרבה עולה? v'kashya yeish chatas shek'reiva olah?
When can you ever repurpose a חטאת chatas as an עולה? olah?
The only time we heard of some קדושה kedusha transferring was a
פסח pesach can become a שלמים, shelamim, right? When have you ever
heard? You can redeem it, you can use the money for, but
whoever says that a חטאת chatas can all of a sudden, oh
it's the end of the year, I can't use it for חטאת,
chatas, I'll just use it for a generic עולה. olah. Since when
can you do that?
ומקייצין u'm'kayitzin like the לשון lashon of קיץ המזבח.
kayitz hamizbeach. Not מוקצה. muktza. They say it more
means—they say קיץ kayitz refers to basically almost like a dessert. Or
I had a רבי who once said it's on a summer break
when the קיץ—when kayitz the מזבח mizbeach is, you know,
needs some extra things to be going on there. Maybe it comes
from that word, but
perhaps—is
it קץ כל בשר keitz kol basar like the end? So קיץ
המזבח kayitz hamizbeach like you know, you've nothing else, it's like the
end of it.
Right, I thank you.
I think that's where they say the idea of קיץ kayitz as
dessert comes from, but the idea of sort of what's leftover and
what's left in—so again, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you normally go
by the rules, שמואל Shmuel. says you can redeem it תמים, tamim,
but here the גמרא gemara says maybe even according to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan you can you know just go ahead and repurpose it,
which is like wild. Okay, so we're not going to let you
redeem the תמים, tamim, but since when can you repurpose a חטאת
chatas into an עולה? olah? So וקשיא יש חטאת שקרבה עולה? v'kashya
yeish chatas shek'reiva olah? אמר רבי יוסי, שאני שאין קרבנות ציבור נקבעין
אלא בשחיטה. shani she'ein korbanos tzibbur nikva'in ela b'sh'chita. No, no, no,
here's the rule that you never knew, which is that a קרבן
ציבור korban tzibur, even after it's sanctified, its full identity does not
get fixed until it's slaughtered. Okay? So I can sanctify this animal
for a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur. as an עולה olah or a
חטאת, chatas, but it's still like generic until the moment I slaughter
it. So therefore you can
change its status. So that might tell you something about the mechanics.
The mechanics that gives us the flexibility is somehow assumed that when
we sanctify הקדש, hekdesh we always leave it open-ended until the last
moment. So that at least gives us the ability to. I have
no idea. We just sort of, we allow ourselves to work within
these parameters. אמר רבי חייא, Amar Rabbi Chiya, תנאי בית דין היא
tnai beis din hee על המותר שיקרבו עולות. al hamotar sheyikrevu olos.
And this is maybe less of saying it's the natural mechanics and
more saying it's proactively, you know, we stipulate and we give ourselves
that latitude. So one sort of says it's one of the natural
rules that you didn't know about until this moment, which is is
that a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur doesn't get its full identity till
שחיטה. shechita. And the other says no, it's not a natural rule,
it is a violation of the rules, but we are sort of
stipulating how we want the קדושה kedusha to work. And as we
saw, that's necessary for what we talked about yesterday, that you use
the תרומה truma funds that are supposed to be for קרבנות korbanot.
and you use it to pay for other things as well, like
for the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim that are teaching about the קרבנות
korbanot. and so on. Okay, so at the end here we got
to sort of see what was implicit about this issue about what
sort of latitude we allow ourselves not only with the funds but
even with the things bought with the funds. Okay, let's take a
look now that we actually get to today's דף on יב עמוד
א, yud beis amud aleph, the משנה, mishna okay? And I think
that hopefully this דף goes pretty quickly. Well, I always hope for
that, I always say that, so let's see. Okay. המקדיש נכסיו, Haktish
nechasav, at least we have the benefit of it being a little
bit repeating what we said before. This is the משנה mishna quoted
before.
המקדיש נכסיו Hamakdish nechasav. והיו בהן דברים ראויים לקרבנות ציבור, tzibur okay,
and amongst your things were something that could be used for קרבן
ציבור, korban tzibur, which we're going to say was קטורת, that's the
only thing that's limited to only be a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur.
ינתנו לאומנין בשכרן. yinatnu le'umnin bischaran. Fine. So what are you supposed
to do with this? You can't actually, the assumption is you can't
actually use it for קטורת itself, because it was a יחיד donation,
it was not a ציבור's tzibur donation, and remember we learned that
even if we'll accept a יחיד's donation if he gives it over
to the ציבור for like other things like the cloak of the
כהן גדול, kohen gadol, we're not going to accept it for the
קרבן korban, itself. The קרבן ציבור korban tzibur. has to be bought
with ציבור funds. So he sanctified this קטורת, it can only be
used for a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, but we can't use it
for a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur? So what are we going to
do?
So דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. Yeah, you use it to
pay the people that make the קטורת. Just like what we alluded
to before, that you use it to pay. Now of course the
problem is that before we said, it's all,
you only desanctify then you use it to pay. So that doesn't
explain how you can, you know, go ahead and do this. So
אמר לו בן עזאי, amar lo Ben Azzai, so that's what Ben
Azzai
said. No, no. The assumption here is and we'll see this as
we continue in the משנה, mishna that things that are fit for
קרבנות, korbanot even though you had a generic הקדש, hekdesh, and generic
הקדש hekdesh means לבדק הבית, lebedek habayit, those things ultimately have to
be wind up being used for קרבנות. korbanos We'll see it more
as we continue the משנה, Mishna. okay? But let's first now focus
on the fact that this does have קדושה, kedusha, can't go straight
to בדק הבית, bedek habayit, what do you do with it? So
Rabbi Akiva says you pay the אומנין. umnin. So אמר לו בן
עזאי אינה היא המדה, amar lo Ben Azzai eina hee hamida, that's
not the way you do things, because basically as the גמרא Gemara.
will explain, where does the קדושה kedusha go? How do you give
this to the workers, what happened to the קדושה? kedusha? אלא, Ella,
and now he tells us the trick we learned yesterday, מפרישים מהן
שכר האומנין, mafrishim mehen sechar ha'umnin, you take out the money you
were going to pay the אומנין, umnin, ומחללין אותם על המעות, umechallelin
osam al hama'ot, then you transfer the קדושה kedusha of the קטורת
to the money, ועל מעות האומנין ונותנין אותם לאומנין, v'al ma'ot ha'umnin
venotnin osam la'umnin, then you give the קטורת to the אומנין, umnin,
because now it's desanctified, בשכרן וחוזרין ולוקחין אותם מתרומה חדשה, bischaran vechozrin
velokechin osam mitruma chadasha, and now you can repurchase it and use
it for the קטורת, okay? So that's how you're able to do
this, but notice according to Ben Azzai you redeemed the קטורת, and
this was the גמרא's Gemara question before, how can you redeem the
קטורת if it was done in a כלי שרת, right? So that
was the answer which is that somehow this was you know that
this was what was the answer to that? Oh it's שמואל. Shmuel
שמואל sort of gives you that latitude, you know once something is
left over or once something sort of can't be used that way
and it's for the קרבן korban, ציבור. Okay so this is Ben
Azzai sort of says the trick we knew, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
somehow figures out that you can give it to them even though
it's קדוש kadosh and we'll have to see about that. Okay, now
we talk about everything
else. המקדיש נכסיו והיו בהן בהמה ראויה לגבי המזבח. Haktish nechasav vehayu
bahen behema reuya gabai hamizbe'ach. Now let's say it's not something for
a קרבן korban. ציבור, but it's only basically animals which are ראוי
for you to bring as a קרבן? korban Okay, pretty much anything
else would be fit for you to bring as a קרבן. korban
So what is the nature of the קדושה kedusha since you gave
it you were generically מקדיש maktish your stuff? זכרים ונקבות. zecharim unekevot.
You had male and female animals. רבי אליעזר אומר זכרים ימכרו לצרכי
עולות ונקבות ימכרו לצרכי זבחי שלמים. Rabbi Eliezer omer zecharim yimachru l'tzorchei
olot u'nekevot yimachru l'tzorchei zivchei shelamim. So an עולה ola can only
be male, a שלמים shelamim can be either male or female. So
his basic position is the following. We do not split your קדושה.
kedusha. Generic קדושה kedusha is for בדק הבית. bedek habayit So even
these animals are owned by בדק הבית, bedek habayis they're owned by
the temple treasury for the you know the funds for repairs for
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay but we've got a problem. Once
something is in the hands of הקדש, hekdesh whatever type of הקדש
hekdesh it is, whether בדק הבית bedek habayis whatever, if it's something
that fits for for bringing a קרבן, korban, we we don't want
to see that like having been in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash.
as it were and I mean not figuratively that you dragged them
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and then and it could have
been used It wasn't used. So here's what we're going to do.
We're going to sell this nice sheep that's זכר zachar that could
be used as a קרבן, korban but it's only sanctified for temple
funds. We're going to sell it to you Norm as a because
we know you need to bring an עולה. olah. So you'll pay
us for it. The קדושה kedusha of this animal will transfer to
the money, like that'll become our בדק הבית bedek habayis money. And
you'll have an animal to bring as an עולה. olah. So now
we accomplished both. The animal got brought as an עולה olah because
he bought it and he re-sanctified it, because we removed the קדושה
kedusha of בדק הבית bedek habayis. from it, right? And then the
money now we have to use for בדק הבית bedek habayis. purposes.
That clear? Yes? Okay.
Couldn't you have just sold it to the to the שקל shekel
fund to bring as a קרבן korban, ציבור?
Why could we not have what would have removed the where would
we have transferred the קדושה kedusha on? We would have needed new
unsanctified funds to transfer the קדושה kedusha on.
But can't you use the money from the שקל? shekel?
That's
קדוש kadosh already. That's already קדוש. kadosh. You can't transfer קדושה kedusha
onto something already קדוש. kadosh. So what we do is we transfer
it on the money of the person buying the animal. He winds
up bringing the animal. And now we've got the money that goes
to the בדק הבית. bedek habayis. Okay, so that's what it means
לצורכי עולות. l'tzorchei olos. זכרים ימכרו לצורכי עולות, Zacharim yimachru l'tzorchei olos,
sold to people that need to bring an עולה. olah. נקבות, Nekeivos,
the females, ימכרו לצורכי זבחי שלמים, yimachru l'tzorchei zivchei shelamin, are sold
to people that need to bring a שלמים. shelamin. ודמיהם, Vedmeihem, the
money we got from those sales, יפלו עם שאר נכסים לבדק הבית,
yi'plu im she'ar nechasim l'bedek habayis, gets put in with all the
rest of the stuff for בדק הבית. bedek habayis, And the animals
get brought as a קרבן. korban. רבי יהושע אומר, Reb Yehoshua omer,
now רבי יהושע Reb Yehoshua doesn't like that. He wants the actual
קרבן korban. animals themselves, the קדושה kedusha that was originally made to
basically be defined, basically he understands it was a generic קדושה. kedusha.
So what type of קדושה kedusha it was is defined by the
object that's caught in its net. So for my house and my
car and my furniture, that's בדק הבית. bedek habayis. But for the
animal, the קדושה kedusha becomes a קדושת קרבן kedushas korban because it
was generic. So we'll say that for the animals, I meant to
sanctify it as a קרבן korban, itself. So that's what רבי יהושע
אומר. Reb Yehoshua omer. זכרים עצמן יקרבו עולות. Zacharim atzman yikrevu olos.
No, if you have male unblemished animals, then they get brought as
an עולה olah for you. That's how the קדושה kedusha expresses itself
when it hits those animals. ונקבות, Unekeivos, the females, ימכרו לצורכי זבחי
שלמים ויביא בדמיהם עולות. yimachru l'tzorchei zivchei shelamin veyavi bidmeihem olos. Now
why do you can you not bring the animals as a שלמים?
shelamim? Because he says here's the one limitation. When you sanctify something
for בדק הבית, bedek habayis which is your סתם קדושה, stam kedusha,
it all goes to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. If you sanctify
something as an עולה, olah, it all gets burned. If you sanctify
something as a שלמים, shelamim, you eat most of most of it.
So that's not enough of the same type. We can't make a
generic קדושה kedusha which is fundamentally לבדק הבית l'bedek habayis and transfer
it into a קדושה kedusha for a שלמים. shelamim. It's too much
of the thing what you do with the object is too different.
So therefore what we say is that the object gets the קדושה
kedusha of
an עולה, olah, because it's an animal, ironically. Because it's an animal,
although it can't be an עולה, olah, but the only קרבן קדושה
korban kedusha of that we can allow to happen here is that
of an עולה, olah, because that's the one that's fully to the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash? So this female sheep gets the קדושה kedusha
of an עולה. olah. So what do you do? You sell the
sheep to somebody who needs to bring a שלמים, shelamim, so the
animal itself gets brought in the way it can be brought. ויביא
בדמיהם עולות, Veyavi bidmeihem olos, and you use the proceeds to buy
an עולה. olah. So he basically says for animals the קדושה kedusha
is a קדושה kedusha of an עולה olah that takes effect on
the animal. ושאר נכסים יפלו לבדק הבית. U'shear nechasim yi'plu l'bedek habayis.
And everything else goes to בדק הבית. bedek habayis. אמר רבי עקיבא,
Amar Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, רואה אני את דברי
רבי אליעזר מדברי רבי יהושע. ro'eh ani es divrei Rebbe Eliezer midivrei
Rebbe Yehoshua. You know, both of them were his רבנים, rebbeim, but
he said, he said,
and the גמרא, Gemara remember the גמרא Gemara beforehand had said since
when can a תלמיד talmid be מכריע machria what his רבנים rebbeim
said, but anyway here רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying which one
he says. He did become a חבר. chaver. It's true. But anyway
here רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, רואה אני את דברי רבי אליעזר
מדברי רבי יהושע. ro'eh ani es divrei Rebbe Eliezer midivrei Rebbe Yehoshua.
I like רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. רבי אליעזר's Rebbe Eliezer position that
everything is בדק הבית bedek habayis. makes more sense than רבי יהושע's.
Reb Yehoshua שרבי אליעזר השוה מדותיו, SheRebbe Eliezer hishveh midosav, ורבי
יהושע חלק. veRebbe Yehoshua hillek. רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer makes it consistent.
Everything is בדק הבית. bedek habayis רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says this
קדושה kedusha becomes a different קדושה kedusha when it hits animals. By
the way it's quite fascinating at the beginning of the משנה Mishna
בן עזאי Ben Azzai said to him אינו מן המדה. eino min
hamiddah. And now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying about these you
know which one he likes. This one is השוה מדותיו. hishveh midosav.
So very interesting now he gets use it on someone else. אמר
רבי פפייס, Amar Rabbi Pappias, interesting name, שמעתי כדברי שניהם. shamati k'divrei
sheneihem.
You know I actually heard both, meaning both approaches, meaning that it
depends. Quite fascinating you know which one he. depends on the circumstances.
Here's how that works.
המקדיש בפירוש, Hamakdish b'feirush, if you're explicit, כדברי רבי אליעזר. k'divrei Rabbi
Eliezer. Then we go like Rabbi Eliezer that says it's all לבית
הבית. l'veit habayit. Now what does it mean explicit? So you could
say you actually said המקדיש הכל לבית הבית, Hamakdish hakol l'veit habayit,
but then it's a little obvious. So what המפרשים hamifarshim say is
now what you say is I am מקדיש makdish all of my
property and all of my animals, and you say animals explicitly. Now
you would say maybe אדרבה adaraba if he says that you made
them a separate category, maybe it's a separate קדושה. kedusha. But since
I am identifying animals and I am not and I have an
opportunity to say you know and my animals for קרבנות korbanos and
I don't, then that basically says I want everything to be the
same. That's at least the way to read it. If it's בפירוש
b'feirush then it's like Rabbi Eliezer. המקדיש סתם, Hamakdish stam,
if you just say המקדיש hamakdish everything, then כדברי רבי יהושע. k'divrei
Rabbi Yehoshua. Then actually it'll go like Rabbi Yehoshua that each thing
as appropriate to it and the קדושה kedusha will sort of define
itself on the basis of what objects were there. המקדיש hamakdish נכסיו.
Now last example. והיו בהן דברים הראויים לגבי המזבח, v'hayu bahen devarim
hara'uyim legabei hamizbeach, things fit for the מזבח mizbeach which is sort
of what we were talking about, but now it's not as קרבנות.
korbanot, Other things or not as animals קרבנות. korbanot, יינות ושמנים, yeinot
u'shmanim, wine, oil, that could be used as a as a מנחה,
mincha, the oil, ועופות, v'ofot, birds. Interesting that is an animal קרבן,
but somehow it's put in a different category. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi
Eliezer omer, Rabbi Eliezer says ימכרו לצורכי אותו המין. yimakru l'tzorchei oto
hamin. So you sell those things for people that need to bring
wine נסכים nesachim or people that need the oil for מנחות menachot
or people that need birds. So the animals are the things are
getting used for their purpose. Okay, because that they have to get
used once they were in the פרשה. parsha But what do you
do with the proceeds? שיביא בדמיהן עולות, sheyavi bidmeihen olot, the proceeds
get used for an עולה, olah, which is sort of like a
Rabbi Yehoshua approach. The problem is this is Rabbi Eliezer talking. So
what the heck is he saying that use the proceeds for עולות?
olot? So a number of the commentators in order to deal with
this problem switch the גרסא girsa to רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar as
opposed to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, that would be a different
opinion. You could say that maybe for some bizarre reason Rabbi Eliezer
would agree to Rabbi Yehoshua's approach when you're not talking about you
know animals or large animals, when you're talking about inanimate things or
birds somehow now I agree with Rabbi Yehoshua. But what's the logic
for it? Okay, but here basically it's essentially a Rabbi Yehoshua approach.
You sell the things and they get used themselves and the money
goes for an עולה olah ושאר נכסים יפלו לבית הבית. v'shear nechasim
yiplu l'veit habayit. Everything else goes for לבית הבית. l'veit habayit. So
either for some reason Rabbi Eliezer himself distinguishes between livestock and other
things or this is a third opinion. Yes.
So first of all this is the משנה Mishna. in תמורה Temurah
as far as I remember, right? Basically. So what's it doing here?
And second of all... so let's say the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash.
needs you know something to plow the הקדש Hekdesh, field. Yeah absolutely.
What do they use? I mean do they have to use an
older animal? It can't be like over you know...
why do they have to use a sanctified animal?
No I'm saying I want to... I know the בית המקדש has
a need. Right. You know. And they you know I heard the
temple treasurer told me...
right so you're מקדיש makdish it לבית הבית l'veit habayit and they
use this cow to plow the field if they needed to do
that. So what's the problem?
They couldn't they'd have to be selling it to buy...
oh no you'd have to do it with something that had a
מום. mum. Okay so only if unblemished. Right. If you actually for
some reason need animals not as קרבנות korbanot they would have to
be with מום. mum.
Or if they'd be too old like
you know for the age necessary.
Yeah and and it's interesting I thought to myself as you were
talking you know like an animal that's pulling a plow whatever it's
inevitable that there'd be some מום mum on that animal.
If that's how it was used before.
And but what's it doing
here? This is like a תמורה Temurah משנה mishna, right?
What it has to do with שקלים Shekalim because the whole thing
was talking about things that were sanctified and left over and what
do you do with the extra proceeds. So it's sort of in
this whole thing about objects that were sanctified and where eventually they
go to and get used. But yeah it's a good question what's
it doing here. Okay. המקדיש לקרבנות ציבור. Hamakdish l'korbanot tzibur.
So anyway what how do you explain what you know what is
Rabbi Akiva this whole issue of Rabbi Akiva saying you pay the
money straight to the קטורת straight to the אומנים? umanim? רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan אמר קטורת. So first of all what is this thing
that's only for קרבנות ציבור? korbanot tzibur? This is what we quoted
before, קטורת. אמר רבי יהושע Amar Rabbi Yehoshua and this is the
direct repetition of what we said. תנתן לאומנים בשכרן. tinaten l'umanim bischaran.
Now how could... now how do you deal with the opinion that
says that again that a קטורת can only be made in כלי
שרת? Where'd this guy get קטורת made in a כלי שרת? So
he says oh if קטורת could only be made in a כלי
שרת he got it because it was used to pay him in
the past. He's one of the workers that get paid in קטורת
at least according to Rabbi Akiva they get paid in קטורת. שהיו
נותנים בשכרן
קטורת. shehayu notnim bischaran ketoret. Okay. מאי טעמא דבן עזאי? Mai ta'ama
d'Ben Azzai? So that we did before. What's Ben Azzai's reason he
doesn't like saying you can use it to pay? שאין הקדש מתחלל
על המלאכה she'ein hekdesh mitchalel al hamelacha אלא על המעות. ela al
hame'ot. It's like what we were talking about yesterday. You can't transfer
הקדש Hekdesh to something abstract. You did your work I'm paying you.
Where did the קדושה kedusha go? It went to the work that
you did. The work isn't a thing. The קדושה kedusha has to
transfer to another object. So he says a very simple thing. What
would Rabbi Akiva say? I don't know. Maybe you would say it
can transfer to abstract מלאכה melacha which is a fascinating idea. Maybe
again it's one of these things which we just somehow stipulate although
it's quite interesting because here we're not
stipulating. Actually this is a private הקדש, Hekdesh so it's not exactly
clear where רבי עקיבא's Rebbe Akiva position is there.
כל מה שדעת רבנן אדעתא.
Kol
mah she'daas Rabonan adaata. Something.
That's a cute one. Okay, very cute. Okay, so, I love these
jokes that like it's total internal, only my yeshiva guys get these
jokes. My brother was once at a קידוש Kiddush and was פרשת
חיי שרה Parshas Chayei Sarah and they were serving kichel. So the
guy next to him says, כחלא כחלא משתעי. Kichla kichla mishtaya. You
got it. תמן תנינא. Taman tanina. Okay. יש בקדשי בדק הבית. Yesh
b'kodshei bedek habayis. No WASP, no
North African Jew would think that was funny. Okay anyway, okay, right.
Because of the, anyway, fine. תמן תנינא. Taman tanina.
Now, we've taught over
there,
okay, a ברייתא, Baraita, meaning, or what, we've taught over there
the following which teaches differences, what's unique about קדשי בדק הבית kodshei
bedek habayis as opposed to קדשי מזבח. kodshei mizbeach. תמן תנינא. Taman
tanina. יש בקדשי בדק הבית. Yesh b'kodshei bedek habayis. Here are the
following unique characteristics of קדשי בדק הבית: kodshei bedek habayis: שסתם הקדשות
לבדק הבית. she'stam hekdeshos l'bedek habayis. First of all, your, when you
say המקדיש without being specific, it goes לבדק הבית. l'bedek habayis. That's
our משנה. mishna, Okay.
By the way, I want to point out that that's a surprise.
We always talk about הקדש Hekdesh? as sort of owning things for
their value to use for their needs as בדק הבית. bedek habayis
But actually what we learned in the previous משנה mishna, is that
there's a lot of funds that are not בדק הבית bedek habayis
funds that are also used for needs, like שירי הלשכה shirei halishka
could have been a huge fund to pay for building the walls
and this and that, and it wasn't a בדק הבית bedek habayis
fund. So it's interesting that when you say סתם הקדש, stam Hekdesh,
it doesn't just mean like if I write a check out to
the Hebrew Institute of Riverdale, they get to decide which fund they
want to put it in. Right? So why דוקא davka it goes
to the בדק הבית bedek habayis fund and not to the other
funds is interesting. But it could be that the other funds were
defined as שירי הלשכה shirei halishka as coming from the לשכה or
coming from the leftover תרומת הלשכה. trumas halishka. So the only fund
that I could contribute to was the בדק הבית bedek habayis. fund.
Because even though those could have been huge funds and the needs
that they served were big, ultimately it was set up that that
only came from the שקל shekel and שירי הלשכה shirei halishka and
so on. So anyway, that's worth just remembering that this is not
the only fund in the בית המקדש. So סתם הקדשות לבדק הבית.
stam hekdeshos l'bedek habayis. הקדש בדק הבית חל על
הכל. Hekdesh bedek habayis chal al hakol. הקדש hekdesh of בדק הבית
bedek habayis can put be, can go on any object, you know,
anything in the world you can be מקדיש makdish for בדק הבית.
bedek habayis, As opposed to קרבנות korbanot? which are only unblemished animals
and so on. ומועלים בגידוליהן. U'moalin b'giduleihen.
Now, things that come from things that I sanctified, there's מעילה. me'ila.
And here's a very important difference. The קדושה kedusha of בדק הבית
bedek habayit. is basically, I mean this I'm going to simplify it
a little bit, but it's basically קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. It's a
קדושה kedusha for the use of the thing for the, for its
value. You know, what do they say that's what a cynic is,
somebody who knows the cost of everything and the value of nothing.
Anyway, so this is only for cost thing. Not, anyway. This is
something that's only for its monetary value. And its basic relationship to
the בית המקדש is that it's owned by the בית המקדש. Whereas
a קרבן is something that its sanctity is about its use. This
animal is going to be used and it's not necessarily defined in
terms of its sanctity by being owned by the בית המקדש. Think
if I sanctify an animal for שלמים. shelamim. Do I own it,
does the בית המקדש own it, right? It's not defined by its
own being owned by the בית המקדש. So here's the difference. Maybe
it's a little ironic. If this thing that I sanctified has fruit,
I sanctified a field and trees and it bore fruit, I sanctified
an animal and we milked it and we sheared it. Is that
owned by the בית המקדש? Well, if it's בדק הבית, bedek habayit,
the answer is yes, it was their property. Their property got, you
know, made a profit or whatever, of course they own it. But
if it's a קרבן, so and let's say it's an animal and
I milk and I shear it, right? That's not its identity as
a קרבן. That's completely secondary. Is that מעילה? me'ila? No, so there's
no, am I allowed to shear it? There's an איסור issur to
do גיזה giza on קדשים kodashim and so on. Let's ignore that
for a moment and let's or let's say it got pregnant and
it had a child, it was a female. Okay, we'll ignore whether
it was allowed to be done, but does the, is the thing
that comes off of it הקדש? hekdesh, And the answer is no,
because that קדושה kedusha was about its identity and purpose and this
is extraneous to that and it's not about being owned by the
בית המקדש. Okay, so,
where were
we? ומועלים בגידוליהן. U'moalin b'giduleihen. That's specifically about קדשי בדק הבית. kodshei
bedek habayis. ואין בהם הנאה לכהנים. V'ein bahem hana'ah l'kohanim. And the
כהנים kohanim will never get any benefit out of it because it
goes all for repairs as opposed to קרבנות where they can get
the, even by an עולה, olah, they get the skin and the
leather. אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chanina, now that's the ברייתא. Baraita.
So אמר רבי חנניה, Amar Rabbi Chananya, excuse me, רבי אלעזר הוא.
Rabbi Elazar hu. That's, goes like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of our
משנה. mishna דתני D'tani because As רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, the
הקדש hekdesh is always the בדק הבית. bedek habayit. That's
right, דתנינא, detanina, we saw in our משנה, mishna המקדיש חטאתו והיתה
בהן בהמה ראויה לגבי מזבח, hamakdish chatato vehayetah bahen behemah re'uyah legabei
mizbe'ach, זכר ונקבה, zachar un'keivah, רבי אליעזר אומר זכרים ימכרו לצורכי עולות
ונקבות ימכרו לצורכי זבחי שלמים ודמיהם יפלו עם שאר נכסיו לבדק הבית.
Rabbi Eliezer omer zacharim yimachru letzorchei olot un'keivot yimachru letzorchei zivchei shelamim
udemaihem yiplo im shear nechasav lebedek habayit. So he says, yes, סתם
הקדש לבדק הבית, stam hekdesh lebedek habayit, even by animals. That's רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position. The animals themselves should get used by the
people we sell them to, but the הקדש, the סתם הקדש לבדק
הבית stam hekdesh lebedek habayit for סתם. stam? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, טעמא דרבי אליעזר, ta'ama deRabbi Eliezer, the reasoning of רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, איש כי יקדיש את ביתו קדש לה', ish ki
yakdish et beito kodesh l'Hashem, right? So that's the פסוק, pasuk, the
one פסוק pasuk in the תורה Torah that talks about sanctifying your
property. במה עסקינן? Bamah askinan? What's the case here? במה עסקינן? Bamah
askinan? What would you say about? אי דבית דירה, Ei debeit dirah,
if it wants to say your house, it means literally your house,
the place you live. כבר כתיב, Kvar ketiv, ואם המקדיש יגאל את
ביתו. ve'im hamakdish yigal et beito. Well, we mentioned house in another
פסוק. pasuk. So בית here doesn't mean house. אלא במה עסקינן? Ela
bamah askinan? What are we talking about here? במקדיש נכסיו, B'makdish nechasav,
means your household, everything in your house. I sanctify my house, he's
like I sanctify all of my property. That's what it says. מכאן
שסתם הקדשות לבדק הבית. Mikan shestam hekdeshot lebedek habayit. And the פרשה
there says יקדיש את ביתו yakdish et beito and it doesn't say
בדק הבית, bedek habayit? but anyway it talks about it going towards
being owned by the Temple and going towards the Temple. So he
says, look, the פסוק pasuk says you sanctify, it goes to the
Temple, so it's all בדק הבית. bedek habayit. Of course it's pretty
funny because it's generic in that פסוק, pasuk, maybe it would have
a different treatment if we'd, you know, if we were talking about
animals. Anyway, that's his position, סתם הקדש לבדק הבית. stam hekdesh lebedek
habayit. אמר רבי זעירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, רב הונא בשם רב, Rav
Huna b'shem Rav, במה פליגין? b'meh paligin? When do they debate about
how the קדושה kedusha affects my animal? What type of קדושה kedusha
it takes effect on my animals, I should say. במקדיש נכסיו, B'makdish
nechasav, when you just, you know, you מקדיש makdish all your property
and some of that was animals. אבל המקדיש עדרו, Aval hamakdish edro,
let's say I go over to my flock and I say, and
I have my whole flock of sheep and I'm saying, I am
מקדיש makdish this flock of sheep. So what would we say there?
There you don't have to talk about different קדושה kedusha that goes
on the car and a different קדושה kedusha on the sheep, it's
all sheep. So in that case, אבל המקדיש עדרו, aval hamakdish edro,
כולי עלמא מודי שהיא למזבח. kulei alma modei shehi l'mizbe'ach. Everybody would
say there that if it's only animals that could be brought as
קרבנות, then and you don't have to say it takes effect different
ways, then even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would agree it's all קדושת
מזבח. kedushat mizbe'ach. רבי בא בר הונא בשם רב, Rabbi Ba bar
Huna b'shem Rav, so that's one opinion. Now there's another opinion in
the name of רב. Rav. No. במה פליגין במקדיש עדרו? Mah paligin
b'makdish edro? Actually the debate in the משנה, mishna this is really
hard to read in the משנה, mishna the debate in the משנה
mishna. was when you sanctified your flock. That was exactly the debate
in the משנה mishna and even there רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says,
and that's where they debate and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says even
there
it doesn't go for a קרבן. אבל במקדיש נכסיו, Aval b'makdish nechasav,
if you really had like a, you know, all different types of
property, כולי עלמא מודי שהיא לבדק הבית. kulei alma modei shehi lebedek
habayit. Even רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, would agree it's לבדק הבית. lebedek
habayit. That's a really hard read in the משנה mishna because the
משנה mishna, makes it clear that other than the animals, there's other
things that are going לבדק הבית. lebedek habayit. Okay? So על דעתיה
דרבי זעירא ניחא. al da'ateih deRabbi Zeira nicha. So רבי זעירא Rabbi
Zeira works in the משנה. mishna דקשיא על דרבי בא, Dekashya al
deRabbi Ba, but רבי בא Rabbi Ba doesn't work in the משנה
mishna because the משנה mishna says בהמה לאו למזבח היא? behemah lav
l'mizbe'ach hi? Isn't an animal go to the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Meaning in
our משנה, mishna right? We said that, hold on, let me just
see how, just, yeah, how you read this. One minute.
Yeah, exactly. Meaning, how does our משנה mishna say, oh you sell
the animals that are needed as קרבנות, you know, you sell the
animals as קרבנות and that goes with everything else לבדק הבית. lebedek
habayit. If the whole case is a case of only animals, and
that's the only case they debate, and otherwise they agree that the
הקדש is split, so what's the other stuff that goes to בדק
הבית? bedek habayit. Right? The משנה mishna says you sell the animals
and that gets goes for an עולה olah according to רבי יהושע,
and the other stuff goes for בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayit. What's the
other stuff?
If it's all animals, בהמה לאו למזבח היא? behemah lav l'mizbe'ach hi?
Everything is going to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. בהמה למזבח היא, Behemah l'mizbe'ach
hi, yeah, you're right, it does go to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So
למה סתם האיש הזה, lamah stam ha'ish hazeh, who's כאומר לא יהא
אלא לבדק הבית? ke'omer lo yehei ela lebedek habayit? So but why
did this person say it סתם? Why didn't he say I'm מקדיש
makdish this as קרבנות? To say that he wanted some of it
at least to go to בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayit, Now the question
is which one? Hold on.
One minute. Hold on one second. I think probably the animals that
are not fit. I think we're about to say that. One minute.
Whatever. Older animals or with a מום. mum. One minute. Just one
second. Let me
just see
turn... I'm not seeing the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explicitly explaining that, but
I imagine what you would have to say here is, is it
means that the rest of the, that the, that even though it's
קרבנות *Korbanos* and they're all fit for it, some of it would
still be לבדק הבית *l'Bedek ha-Bayis* because he said it סתם *stam*,
so presumably those animals that are not fit, either because they're too
old or they have מום mum, *mum* or something. But clearly it's
a very hard read of the משנה mishna *Mishna*. Hold on, I
hear the גליון הש"ס *Gilyon ha-Shas*. Just one minute.
Hold on.
Yeah, yeah, that's what the גליון הש"ס *Gilyon ha-Shas* basically says, that
the animals that cannot be used as a קרבן *korban*, those would
be לבדק הבית *l'Bedek ha-Bayis*. Okay, but again, it's a very hard
read of the משנה mishna *Mishna* that we're only talking about animals.
Okay, so we basically have one opinion that the משנה mishna *Mishna*
is talking about mixed property, which makes sense, but if it's all
animals, everybody agrees it's קרבנות *korbanos*. The other approach is that the
משנה mishna *Mishna* is talking about only animals, and the debate would
be about the animals that were not normally fit for a קרבן
*korban*, that's where they can debate, but if it's really mixed, everybody
agrees it's all לבדק הבית *l'Bedek ha-Bayis*. And now we get the
third position. Okay, so it says like this: רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*Rabbi Yochanan* אמר *amar* לא שנו *lo shanu*, לא שנה *lo shana*.
It doesn't make a difference what the scenario is. היא המקדיש נכסיו
*hi hamakdish nechasav*, היא המקדיש עדרו *hi hamakdish edro*, היא המחלוקת *hi
hamachlokes*. You like the way of saying it, right? It doesn't matter
whether it's mixed property, whether it's all sheep, it's the same debate.
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* would always say it all goes לבדק הבית
*l'Bedek ha-Bayis* and רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* would say for the animals,
they're going to go for קרבנות *korbanos*. Okay. רב הונא בשם רב
אבו בשם רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rav Huna beshem Rav Avu beshem
Rabbi Yochanan*, קדשי בדק הבית Kodshei Bedek HaBayit *kodshei Bedek ha-Bayis* שפדאן
תמימים *shepadaan temimim* יצאו לחולין *yatzu l'chulin*. Let's say according to רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, you have these animals that are תמימים *temimim*, that
are unblemished and they have קדושת בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit *kedushas Bedek
ha-Bayis*. By the way, everybody would agree that you could do that
intentionally, right? Here the only question is that it's generic, so רבי
יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* says I'm going to interpret it to be קדושת
קרבן *kedushas korban*, but if I go over to my unblemished sheep
and I say I am מקדיש *makdish* this לבדק הבית *l'Bedek ha-Bayis*,
everybody agrees that it's קדוש לבדק הבית *kadosh l'Bedek ha-Bayis*. So you
can, everybody agrees that you can have a scenario of an unblemished
animal that's בדק הבית *Bedek ha-Bayis*. Now you redeem it. What is
the status of that animal? And this gets back to part of
the issue I told you before about the conceptual difference of בדק
הבית *Bedek ha-Bayis* and קדושת קרבן *kedushas korban*. When I normally redeem
בדק הבית *Bedek ha-Bayis*, then it's like a sale, all the things
we talked about before, I pay you, I transfer the money, whatever,
there's no lasting קדושה *kedusha*. The קדושה *kedusha* was only about its
value, and when you substitute something else and you redeem it, it
completely leaves that object. It's all about ownership and value. But when
I מקדיש *makdish* a קרבן *korban*, that קדושה *kedusha* is about identity.
So even when it gets a מום mum? *mum* and I transfer
the קדושה *kedusha* to something else, the fact that it was a
קרבן *korban* still holds onto its identity. And the הלכה halacha *halacha*
is that even after you redeem a קרבן *korban* with a מום
mum, *mum*, you cannot do certain things with it. I mean you
don't use it as a קרבן *korban*, but you're limited. You can't
shear it, you can't milk it, and so on, because that was
about its identity and that still a little bit of that still
stays behind. Okay, but it's not true about בדק הבית *Bedek ha-Bayis*.
So now the question is, you have this unblemished animal that's owned
by בדק הבית *Bedek ha-Bayis*, because everyone would explicitly you explicitly sanctified
it that way. So do we follow normal בדק הבית *Bedek ha-Bayis*
rules and say after you transfer the value it completely can be
used for anything? Or do we still say, you know, it still
was an unblemished animal, maybe somehow there should be some identity aspect
left to that that it does not become completely חולין Chullin? *chulin*?
So רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* would not say that that should be
an הלכה *halacha*, even if I say if you say explicitly he
would not. It's only about generic. So that's the question. קדשי בדק
הבית Kodshei Bedek HaBayit, *Kodshei Bedek ha-Bayis* שפדאן תמימים *shepadaan temimim* that
you redeem them when they were unblemished, which you would again certainly
do for רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, יצאו לחולין *yatzu l'chulin*. They completely
become desanctified, it does not have some remnant status. Gemara says מתניתין
אמר כן Matnitin amar ken? *Matnisin amar kein*. We have a משנה
mishna *Mishna* that says that. It says ולדן וחלבן מותר לאחר פדיונן
veladan ve-chalavan mutar le-achar pidyonan, *veladan vechalavan mutar l'achar pidyonan*. It says
that by קדשי בדק הבית Kodshei Bedek HaBayit *kodshei Bedek ha-Bayis* that
I'm sorry, no, actually מתניתין אמר כן matnitin amar ken *Matnisin amar
kein* is בדמיא *bidmiya*. Does our משנה mishna *Mishna* say that? At
least that's how the מפרשים *meforshim* read it. Because the משנה mishna
*Mishna*, that same משנה mishna *Mishna* that talked about what's unique about
קדשי בדק הבית Kodshei Bedek HaBayit *kodshei Bedek ha-Bayis* and talked about
unique about קדשי מזבח Kodshei Mizbe'ach, *kodshei mizbeiach*, it says that by
קדשי בדק הבית Kodshei Bedek Habayis, *kodshei Bedek ha-Bayis* that the ולד
vlad *velad* and the חלב chalav *chalav* is מותר mutar, *mutar*, right?
That's the idea of excuse me. Let me hold on. Let me
take a step back. One minute,
let me one minute. Yeah. So it says,
right, it
says
hold on.
I'm sorry, just let me just double-check this. Okay. Yeah, so hold
on. Yeah,
so right. Okay, okay, I got it. So anyway, so here's the
basic הלכה, right? After you redeem the, you
know what, I need to check this out in a גמרא. Gemara
Hold on one second. I'm sorry.
I'm sorry. I'm just going to double-check this. I got to make
sure I'm saying this right. Just give me one second. Luckily I
have all of שס Shas on my iPhone.
Just give me one second. Because I, it's a little, there's this
whole,
it's quoting this whole משנה Mishnah about the difference between קדשי בדק
הבית Kodshei Bedek Habayis and קדשי מזבח, Kodshei Mizbe'ach, and it's not
and it's not clear when the ירושלמי Yerushalmi quotes it, which section
of the משנה Mishnah it's quoting from. So I just want to
make sure I'm saying it right. One second. Oh my gosh, look
at that. Almost exactly open to the דף I need. One second.
Where are you
in
חולין?
Chullin It's תמורה ל א עמוד ב.
Temurah Lamed
Aleph Amud Bet.
Oh, תוספות Tosfot says this is חולין chullin. 138. Yeah.
Oh,
yeah.
Hold on one second.
But I have here said before חולין דף ל
א.
Chullin daf
Lamed Aleph.
One second, one second.
One second, one second. And בכורות. Bechoros. Hold on. Hold on.
I
had the גמרא
on the place.
שבועות קח Shavuot Kof Chet and קדשים קח. Kodashim Kof Chet.
Here we
go. Wait a minute. Okay, no, it's a משנה Mishnah in, it's
a משנה in תמורה. Temurah. Here's the משנה in תמורה, Temurah, okay?
יש בקדשי מזבח שאין בקדשי בדק הבית ויש בקדשי בדק הבית שאין
בקדשי מזבח שקדשי מזבח עושין תמורה, Yesh bekodshei mizbe'ach she-ein bekodshei bedek
habayit ve-yesh bekodshei bedek habayit she-ein bekodshei mizbe'ach she-kodshei mizbe'ach osin temurah,
okay, etc., וחייבין עליו משום פיגול נותר וטמא ולינה. ve-chayavin alav mishum
pigul notar ve-tamei ve-linah. Alright,
this is what's unique about קדשי מזבח, Kodshei Mizbe'ach, so it has
all of those הלכות. halachot. ולדן וחלבן אסור לאחר פדיונן. Veladan ve-chalavan
asur le-achar pidyonan.
After you redeem it, even after you redeem it, and this is
about its identity remaining, the children and the milk is forbidden, some
of its identity remains even after it's been redeemed. ושהוחל Ve-she-huchal etc.
מה שאין כן בבדק הבית. Ma she-ein ken be-bedek habayit. יש בקדשי
בדק הבית שסתם הקדשות לבדק הבית. Yesh bekodshei bedek habayit she-stam hekdeshot
le-bedek habayit. הקדש בדק הבית חל על הכל ומועלין בגידוליהן ואין בהם
הנאה. Hekdesh bedek habayit chal al hakol u-moalin bi-giduleihen ve-ein bahem hana'ah.
So here is the question, okay? So I wanted to just, you
know, get it clear which part is about קדשי מזבח, Kodshei Mizbe'ach
which part is about בדק הבית. So let's do this again. Let's,
okay. קדשי בדק הבית שפדאן תמימים יצאו לחולין. Kodshei bedek habayit she-padaan
temimim yatz'u le-chulin.
If you redeem בדק הבית, they go out to חולין. So the
גמרא says like this: מתניתין אמר כן? Does our משנה say that?
The משנה says by קדשי מזבח Kodshei Mizbe'ach that were redeemed, ולדן
וחלבן מותר vladan vechalavan mutar, לאחר פדיונן, that it implicitly says, right,
that the
קדשי מזבח Kodshei Mizbe'ach the ולד and the חלב chalav is אסור,
asur, and by the קדשי בדק הבית, Kodshei Bedek Habayis the children
and the חלב chalav, would be מותר, but only the children and
the חלב, not the actual animal itself. Okay, so that, so, so
that's the question, right? The משנה that says that what's קדשי מזבח
Kodshei Mizbe'ach the animals remain forbidden, implicitly by קדשי בדק הבית the
animals are permissible, okay, but only the animals, not the object itself.
Some of the sanctity remains on the object. So רב חזקיה בשם
רב חסדא Rav Chizkiyah be-shem Rav Chisda says כי פתר שפדאן תמימים
והום ממו. Ki patar she-padaan temimim ve-hu memu. No, no. Here's the
difference. The difference is how did you redeem them? Okay, did you
redeem them or if you redeemed them and once and then they
got a מום, mum. okay, then,
then you can use them for anything. If they remain unblemished, you
can't use them for anything, you can only benefit from their children
and from their milk. Now that's a little bit bizarre, who the
heck cares what happens to them after they were redeemed? Right? So
you have this animal, unblemished, you redeemed it because it was only
בדק הבית and he says when did רבי יוחנן say you can
use it for anything you want after it gets a מום? mum,
So it's clearly some type of like of a rabbinic restriction. You
have something that was unblemished, sanctified, now it's being desanctified, you don't
want to go start ahead and using it to plow the field.
That just looks too funny. So you after, you wait till it
gets a מום, mum and then רבי יוחנן says you can use
it for what you want. When did the משנה say you can
only benefit from its product, like its children and its milk, but
not from the animal itself? That was before it had a מום.
mum. Okay, so that's how we resolve the more limited היתר heter
of the משנה with רבי יוחנן's statement that is a blanket היתר.
heter. רבי יוסי בשם רב חסדא מתניתין אמר כן. Rabbi Yose be-shem
Rav Chisda matnitin amar ken.
Now this is a מתניתין אמר כן as a statement, not a
question. ולדן וחלבן אסור לאחר פדיונן. Veladan ve-chalavan asur le-achar pidyonan. So
because he says look, the case where things are forbidden by קדשי
מזבח Kodshei Mizbe'ach, is when you redeem it after, when you redeem
a קדשי מזבח, Kodshei Mizbe'ach. a קרבן, after it has a מום,
mum, right? So the משנה says again, this is why it's confusing,
is that the משנה says here's what's קדשי מזבח. Kodshei Mizbei'ach After
you redeem it, you can't benefit from the children and the milk.
So implicitly that means קדשי בדק הבית you can benefit from the
children and the milk. Right, but that's only, so then the גמרא
says, ah, that's limited, you can't benefit from the whole thing. So
it doesn't matter whether it got a מום mum, or not. Okay.
So here the גמרא is saying, but look, the case where the
case where what do you call it, the case where קדשי מזבח
Kodshei Mizbei'ach you are, you do redeem it, is already a case
with a מום. So hold on, let me just check one more
time.
Yeah, it's not exactly clear to me how it's an argument, but
the basic argument is the same way by קדשי בדק הבית, by
קדשי מזבח Kodshei Mizbei'ach is the redeeming, you know, it's the case
of being redeemed is after it has a מום, by קדשי מזבח
Kodshei Mizbei'ach as well, by קדשי בדק הבית as well, once it
got a מום, that would give you sort of greater latitude.
Okay, let's say you have... Yeah, I think, I think, I think,
yeah, like
I said, I'm just confused what
the rules are if it has... basically the הלכה is
קדשי מזבח Kodshei Mizbei'ach.
you can never redeem on blemish. Once it's blemished, you can redeem
it, but that only allows you then to, but even after you've
redeemed it, you're not allowed to, to shear it and to... okay.
You know what? I'm glad you asked because I realized that I
was, you know, let me try to write on the board. I
was misstating, I was פארשוויצן farshvitzing and driving everybody crazy.
Sorry,
is there a marker here? No marker?
Anyway, there used to be a marker over there.
It's not there anymore? Oh, there's something. Okay.
Here's what the משנה says. Okay?
It says the difference between קדשי בדק הבית and קדשי מזבח. Okay?
That's what the משנה over there in תמורה Temurah was listing. Okay?
And one of the differences is, it says this says מועלין בגידולין.
mo'alin begidulin. Okay? Right? So we said that's about, that's about its
value. So even if things grow, it's, you can be מועל. mo'el.
And this says, right? That you have a case of ולדן וחלבן
מותר, right?
Because this is about the animal itself, right? And not about its
identity. So, hold on, let me make sure again I'm quoting that
משנה correctly.
No, I got it wrong again. Okay. I'm sorry. I got it
wrong again.
You know what? I think that I need to get this, I
need to get this גמרא a little bit better. We only have
like three minutes left, so why don't we just end here and
we will pick up from here tomorrow? Hopefully I'll be able to
make it clearer then.